Guide to the International Monitor Institute Records, 1986-2006 and undated RL.00604
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute records
1986-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute
RL.00604
530 Linear Feet
The non-profit agency International Monitor Institute (IMI) operated between 1993 and 2003, primarily to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. The International Monitor Institute Records span the dates 1986-2006, and primarily comprise audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations around the world. Countries represented include: Burma (Myanmar), Bosnia and Hercegovina, Cambodia, Kuwait, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, and Thailand. Includes master and use copies of approximately 6000 videocassettes and 100 audio tapes and audiocassettes. The video and audio material is indexed by an extensive database developed by IMI which includes keywords, air dates, segment producer, segment title, and in some cases, transcripts and stills from the video. There are also many photographs and slides taken in the same regions, depicting destruction in areas of conflict, forced labor, refugees and refugee camps, and protests. The majority of the photos were taken on the Burma/Thai border, in Bosnia and Hercegovina, and refugee camps in Rwanda. Finally, there are extensive organizational records, including an extensive database of the audiovisual components. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Approximately 10,100 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The International Monitor Institute Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006, 2007, and 2011.
Biographical Note for Pippa Scott
The International Monitor Institute (IMI) was founded in 1993 by actress and film producer Pippa Scott. Scott, daughter of screenwriter Allan Scott who wrote some of the Astaire-Rogers films, was educated in California and in England, at Radcliffe College and the Southern California Institute of Architecture. Ms. Scott acted in such films as The Searchers and Auntie Mame, and was a founding partner of the Emmy-award winning television company Lorimar Productions (producer of such TV hits as The Waltons and Dallas). Scott established Linden Productions in 1987 to develop documentaries focusing on current issues. Linden's latest production is King Leopold's Ghost, a documentary about the exploitation of the Congo by King Leopold II of Belgium. Scott was a member of the Women's Refugee Commission, the Pacific Council on Foreign Relations, and the Los Angeles World Affairs Council.
Historical Note for International Monitor Institute (IMI)
Organizational History. The International Monitor Institute was founded in 1993 and operated until 2003. Its primary mission was to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. Videos and audiotapes were acquired through donation as well as on collecting trips by IMI associates in the former Yugoslavia, Kuwait, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Iraq, Burma (Myanmar), Thailand, Cambodia, and other countries. IMI's activities also included developing regional archives of videos on conflict and human rights abuses, producing film and multimedia projects to assist humanitarian organizations, organizing public outreach events, conducting video research for governments, film makers, authors, and students, and providing educational outreach. Patrons and partners of IMI and its collections included the International Criminal Court and its staff, Human Rights Watch, Physicians for Human Rights, the Simon Wiesenthal Center, the governments of Bosnia-Hercegovina and Croatia, and former First Lady Hillary Clinton.
Collection Overview
Note: The video and audio tape holdings of the Interntional Monitor Institute records are described in separate finding aids. A large portion of these tapes, particularly that section dealing with the Balkans, is not yet processed. Inventories are currently available for the following sections:
Burma Tapes, circa 1990-2002
Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999
The International Monitor Institute Records span the dates 1986-2006, and primarily consist of audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations around the world. Countries represented include: Burma (Myanmar), Bosnia and Hercegovina, Cambodia, Kuwait, Iraq, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, and Thailand. Includes master and use copies of approximately 6000 videocassettes and 100 audio tapes and audiocassettes. The video and audio material is indexed by an extensive database developed by IMI which includes keywords, air dates, segment producer, segment title, and in some cases, transcripts and stills from the video. There are also six boxes of photographs and slides taken in the same regions, depicting destruction in areas of conflict, forced labor, refugees and refugee camps, and protests. The majority of the photographs, almost all color snapshots, were taken on the Burma/Thai border, in Bosnia and Hercegovina, and refugee camps in Rwanda. One set of seven folders are images taken by staff of the Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children (now known as the Women's Refugee Commission). There are other images that come from United Nations organizations, including the International Refugee Commission. Finally, organizational records from the offices of IMI comprise a significant amount of the materail in this collection, including an extensive database of the audiovisual components and transcripts from war crimes tribunals.
Addition (2007-0070) (approx. 4000 items, 120 linear ft.; dated 1990-2002) contains master and use copies of videocassettes related to human rights violations around the world.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Related Material
International Monitor Institute. Rwanda videotapes and audiotapes, 1992-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Monitor Institute. Burma videotapes, circa 1990-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Women's Refugee Commission records, 1989-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
HU OSA 350, Fonds 350: Records of the International Monitor Institute
Open Society Archives, Central European University
Separated Material
The collection came with an extensive reference library consisting mostly of books and monographs providing historical background to human rights conflicts documented in the collection. Books and monographs published by human rights organizations are individually cataloged in Rubenstein Library. The rest of the collection was integrated into Perkins circulating collection and can be searched by the subject heading Human Rights Archive.
Videocassettes; Trial transcripts; Databases; Audiotapes; Photographs; Slides (photographs); Burma -- Social conditions; Cambodia -- Social conditions; Policía Nacional Civil (El Salvador); El Salvador -- Social conditions; War crimes; Africa -- Social conditions; Asia-Pacific -- Human rights advocacy -- Research; Kuwait -- History -- 20th century; Refugees -- Burma; Rwanda -- Social conditions; Refugees; Refugees -- Rwanda; Radio -- Crimes against peace; Refugee camps; Thailand -- Social conditions; Audiocassettes; Refugees -- Thailand; Sierra Leone -- Social conditions; Iraq -- Social conditions; Environmental degradation; Forced Labor; Refugee camps -- Rwanda; Documentary films -- Political aspects; Justice, Administration of; Peace-building -- Bosnia and Hercegovina; Human rights monitoring; Bosnia and Hercegovina -- Social conditions; ICTY; International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); International Monitor Institute; International Refugee Organization; International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia; Scott, Pippa, 1935-; Radio-Télévision Libre des Mille Collines; Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees; International Tribunal for the Prosecution of Persons Responsible for Serious Violations of International Humanitarian Law Committed in the Territory of theFormer Yugoslavia since 1991; Women's Refugee Commission; United Nations -- Peacekeeping forces
- Photographic Material Series, 1996-2002 and undated, 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains groupings of images taken in areas of conflict around the world which form visual evidence gathered by the United Nations' Human Commission on Refugees (UNHCR). Material includes color photos and slides showing fires burning or villages destroyed and injuries of Burmese refugees, taken in Burma or Thailand by human rights worker Kevin Heppner, founder of Karen Human Rights Group; photos and slides taken in Burma, or on the Thailand/Burma border in refugee camps acquired or made for IMI and gathered or taken by filmmaker, Jeanne Hallacy, who spent time in Bangkok; stills from Mikel Flamm, a professional photographer/journalist; photos and hi-8 video of the refugee camps on the Thailand/Burma border taken by members of the Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children, including IMI founder Pippa Scott, when they visited the camps; and images of refugee camps and refugees chiefly in Rwanda and other countries in Africa, but also in Sri Lanka and Turkey.
  Other images contain scenes of mass demonstrations for peace, possibly in Thailand; forced labor in Thailand; ruined cities in Sarajevo and photos of residents and mass burial sites; elections and voting scenes, possibly from Burma or Thailand; burning oil fields in Kuwait; and other scenarios in countries such as China, Rwanda, Kenya, Cote d'Ivoire, Cambodia, Vietnam, and Pakistan. Many of these photographs can be assumed to have been taken in secret and smuggled out of the country of origin.
  Photographs and slides, along with a few negatives, are arranged by country name, with unidentified images at the end of the sequence. Slides are indicated - the rest are photographs. Most are undated but can be estimated at being from the 1990s to 2000. Also included and filed as found with the images are small amounts of related materials such as newsletters, publicity, and correspondence. There are also a few oversize items at the end of the series.
  - Asia, Cambodia, China, Mongolia, Tibet, slides (Box PH1)
  - Africa, [Rwanda?], 1993 and undated, 2 folders (Box PH1)
  - Bosnia, 9 folders; one page of negative strips, circa 1995 (Box PH1)
  - Bosnia and Herzegovina, 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box PH1A)
  - Bosnia and Sarajevo, 2 folders (Box PH1A)
  - Bosnia, Yugoslavia, Croatia War, slides (Box PH1A)
  - Cambodia, 2 folders (Box PH2)
  - Commission of Experts Offices, March 1994 (Box PH2)
  - Cote d'Ivoire, 2 folders of slides (Box PH2)
  - Croatia, 1993, slides (Box PH2)
  - Eastern Europe, 3 folders of photos, one of slides (Box PH2)
  - Hercegovina, Mostar, 4 folders of negatives, one of photos (Box PH2)
  - IMI Offices, slides (Box PH2)
  - IRC - Rwanda, Zaire, Guinea, Afghanistan, Bosnia, slides (Box PH2)
  - Kuwait, 2 folders (Box PH2)
  - Laos refugee camps, 1998, 2 folders, photos and negatives (Box PH2)
  - Liberia, Monrovia, slides (Box PH2)
  - Mexico (Box PH2)
  - Old Site Images (Separated from Box 666), slides (Box PH2)
  - Pakistan and Khmer Rouge, slides (Box PH2)
  - Rwanda and Kenya (Box PH2)
  - Saga o Sarajevu, circa 1992 (Box PH3)
    Publicity packet of 22 cards with graphics, text, and credits, each one representing a short documentary film about Sarajevo.
  - Sarajevo, 1994 and undated, 4 folders (Box PH3)
  - Thailand and Burma (Myanmar), 1996-1999 and undated, Folders 1-12 of 17 (Box PH3)
  - Thailand and Burma (Myanmar), 1996-1999 and undated, Folders 13-17 of 17 (Box PH4)
  - Thailand and Burma, supporting materials, 1997-1999 (Box PH4)
  - Tribunal slides, Aug. 1999 (Box PH4)
  - Ukraine (Box PH4)
  - United Nations Human Commission on Refugees (UNHCR), 7 folders (Box PH4)
  - UN Commission of Experts, 1994, 3 folders (Box PH4)
  - UN photos, 4 folders (Box PH5)
  - Vietnam, 3 folders (Box PH5)
  - Washington, D.C. and Thailand (?), undated, 2 folders (Box PH5)
  - Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children, 7 folders, photos and slides (Box PH5)
  - Unidentified images, 5 folders, photos and slides (Box PH6)
  - Yugoslavia (Box PH6)
  - Zenice, victims of atrocities (Box PH6)
  - Oversize black and white photograph of actor, unidentified, undated (includes packet of smaller photos in envelope) (Box PH6)
- Organizational Records Series, 1986-2006, 43 boxes
  Series contains documents and records produced and maintained by IMI related to the monitoring of international human rights abuses in the Balkans, Africa, the Middle East, Asia Pacific and other regions, with a bulk of material documenting the genocide in Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia. The series focuses on IMI's searches, solicitation, and acquisition of audiovisual material from various news outlets and production companies, as well as from independent organizations and individuals. The series also has numerous transcripts from the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY) and transcripts of the Radio-Télévision Libres des Milles Collines broadcasts inciting genocide in Rwanda. Other legal files include court transcripts, including victims' testimonies and information regarding the prosecution of war criminals, and legal agreements with various production companies and organizations regarding acquisition of tapes, including information on Linden Productions. Series also contains numerous reports from Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International and the Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children on human rights abuses taking place in various regions. Organizational records include broadcast logs regarding the status of human rights abuses, particularly in the Balkans, Rwanda, and the Middle East. Other organizational files, such as archival summaries and pamphlets, project proposals, travel itineraries regarding conferences and tape acquisitions, newspaper articles, tape search logs and tape annotations and synopses, correspondence, and information on documentary projects and scripts and other artistic representations of human rights abuses and genocide make up the remainder of the collection.
  - Balkan Archives Subseries, 1986-2006 and undated
    Subseries contains documents and records produced and maintained by IMI related to the monitoring of the genocide in the former Yugoslavia. The series focuses on IMI's searches, solicitation, and acquisition of audiovisual material from various news outlets and production companies, such as the BBC, as well as from independent organizations and individuals. The series also has numerous transcripts from the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY). Files include various legal documents and court transcripts, including victims' testimonies and information regarding the prosecution and indictment of Bosnian Serb leaders and generals, such as Slobodan Milesovic, Radovan Karadzic and Rako Mladic, among others. Internal organizational files include correspondence regarding solicitations of material, funding, and IMI's participation in the ICTY, including cooperation with De Paul University College of Law and Professor Cherif Bassiouni; Balkan archive summaries and pamphlets; legal agreements with various production companies and organizations regarding acquisition of tapes; and travel itineraries regarding the same. Many files deal with artistic and documentary representations of the genocide, interviews with Bosnian Serb leaders, and the peace process. Other files include newspaper articles, tape search logs, various printed material, correspondence, publicity material, subject and project files. Additional correspondence can be found under "people" records.
    - ABC News broadcast logs - Bosnia, full-text, 1993 Apr. 8 - 1994 June 9 (Box OR1)
    - ABC videos terms and conditions, 1995 Aug. 17 (Box OR1)
    - Alternativna Informativna Mreza (AIM), a general presentation, 1995 Jan. (Box OR1)
    - Archive preliminary analysis of tapes for International Criminal Tribunal of the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY), 1995 (Box OR1)
    - Archive titles and scene breakdowns, 1993-1994 (Box OR1)
    - Articles on arms, 1996 May (Box OR1)
    - Articles on criminal tribunal and war criminals, 1994-1996 (Box OR1)
    - Articles on elections and Dayton Agreement, 1996 (Box OR1)
    - Articles, general, 1993-2006, 2 folders (Box OR1)
    - Articles on massacre, 1995-1996 (Box OR1)
    - Articles on peace process, 1996 (Box OR1)
    - Articles on Radovan Karadzic and Ratko Mladic, 1996 (Box OR1)
    - Articles on Slobodan Milosevic, 1996 (Box OR1)
    - Artists' statements, 1996 and undated (Box OR1)
    - Balkan Archive description, 1995 and undated (Box OR1)
    - Balkan Archive general, 1993-1999 and undated (Box OR2)
    - Balkan Archive inquiry letters, 1993-1998 (Box OR2)
    - Balkan Archive multimedia database, 1993 and 1996 (Box OR2)
    - Balkan Archive network printouts, 1994 (Box OR2)
    - Balkan Archive notes, undated (Box OR2)
    - Balkans general, 1995 and undated (Box OR2)
    - Balkan war report articles, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box OR2)
    - Bassiouni advocacy regarding DePaul International Human Rights Institute and Linden Productions Agreement, 1993-1997 (Box OR2)
    - BBC - acquisition of film, 1995 May (Box OR2)
    - BBC Television Library Services computer catalogue extracts, 1992 and Mennonite Central Committee (MCC) Resource Catalogue, 2006-2007, 2 folders (Box OR2)
    - BBC Television Library - Yugoslavian situation, 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box OR3)
    - Belgrade/London trip regarding solicitation of materials, 1994-1995 (Box OR3)
    - "Beauty and the Beast" by Christopher Merril, 1994 and undated (Box OR3)
    - BHTV tapes, 1994 (Box OR3)
    - Blood and Honey: Photographs of the Balkan Wars by Ron Haviv, final dummy, undated (Box OR3)
    - Bosnian Institute - Mr. Zulfikarpasic, 1995 and undated (Box OR3)
    - Bosnian Serb leader Dr. Radovan Karadzic talking with David Frost - full broadcast transcript, 1995, Jul. 21 (Box OR3)
    - Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict, 1998-1999 and undated (Box OR3)
    - CBS Public Eye - report about Janko Janjic a.k.a. Tuta, aired, 1997 Oct. 15 (Box OR3)
    - Center for Reproductive Law and Policy, undated (Box OR3)
    - Chronology of peace negotiations (draft), 1993, 2 folders (Box OR3)
    - CNN correspondence and agreements regarding footage, 1994-1995 (Box OR3)
    - Coalition for International Justice - information on whereabouts of 36 indicted war criminals in the former Yugoslavia, 1996 Nov. 26 (Box OR3)
    - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1995 (Box OR4)
    - Community of Bosnia - interview with Michael Sells, undated (Box OR4)
    - Completed itinerary of East coast trip, 1996 (Box OR4)
    - "Concentration Camps" by Ed Vulliamy, undated (Box OR4)
    - Confidentiality agreements (former Yugoslavia), 1993-1995 (Box OR4)
    - Contacts, general, undated (Box OR4)
    - Correspondence, 1993-1999
      - ABC News London correspondence regarding footage from Brcko, 1996 (Box OR4)
      - Balkan War Report correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box OR4)
      - DePaul correspondence regarding archiving tapes, 1993-1994 (Box OR4)
      - Human Rights Watch, Balkan Archive correspondence (Box OR4)
      - International Human Rights Law Institute outreach chron file, 1993-1994 (Box OR4)
      - ITN Archives, correspondence regarding Balkans, 1995-1998 (Box OR4)
      - Letter from Hollywood Women's Political Committee to President Clinton regarding War Crimes Tribunal in Former Yugoslavia, 1993 Aug. 20 (Box OR4)
      - Letter from Justice Louise Arbour to His Excellency Mr. Slobodan Milosevic, 1999 Mar. 26 (Box OR4)
      - Letters of commendation, 1994-1995 (Box OR4)
      - Letters of support for Balkan Archive, 1995 Apr. 14-Oct.24 (Box OR4)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence regarding Balkan Archive, including tapes, 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box OR4)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence A-Z, 1993-1994 (Box OR5)
      - NHK Television, 1993-1994 (Box OR5)
      - Outreach chron file, 1994-1995 (Box OR5)
      - Photo Perspectives regarding Faces of Sorrow (Box OR5)
      - Ron Haviv correspondence, 1999 (Box OR5)
      - Scheffer, David - regarding recommendation as Legal Adviser to Department of State (Box OR5)
      - Senators, Jan. 1994 (Box OR5)
      - Sky News regarding Balkan Archives, 1995 (Box OR5)
      - Sources chron file, 1993 Sep. - 1994, Aug. (Box OR5)
      - Spielberg correspondence, 1993 (Box OR5)
      - United Nations ambassadors - correspondence regarding tapes for in-house viewing, 1994 Jan. (Box OR5)
      - United Nations correspondence, 1995 (Box OR5)
    - "Current Status of Reproductive Healthcare in Former Yugoslavia," undated (Box OR5)
    - Detention places, 1993-1995 (Box OR5)
    - Department of Defense news briefings, 1996 Feb. 13 - 1997 Aug. 21 (Box OR5)
    - Department of State briefing on video tape confirming Kosovo massacre, May 19, 1999 (Box OR5)
    - "East of Bosnia: Refugees in Serbia and Montenegro," 1993 Sep. (Box OR5)
    - "Ethnic Cleansing Genocide in Greater Serbia," edited by Tilman Zulich for the Society for Threatened Peoples (Box OR5)
    - The Eyes of Bosnia... a documentary film, 1993 Feb. (Box OR5)
    - Fama International regarding documentary film The Siege, 1998 (Box OR6)
    - Filmske Novosti with Agreement, 1995 (Box OR6)
    - Film tracking - ABC Balkans, 1993-1995 (Box OR6)
    - Film tracking and people, Bosnia/Yugoslavia, 1993 (Box OR6)
    - Final draft of Task Force on War Crimes in the Former Yugoslavia report, 1993 June (Box OR6)
    - Final version of Task Force on War Crimes in the Former Yugoslavia report, 1993 Jul. 8 (Box OR6)
    - Flyers, etc., 1995 (Box OR6)
    - Footage outreach for Balkan Archives, 1993-1994 (Box OR6)
    - Forging War: The Media in Servia, Croatia, and Bosnia-Hercegovina by Mark Thompson, undated (Box OR6)
    - Fox News, Balkans, 1993-1999 (Box OR6)
    - Hague notes and information, 1994-1995 and undated (Box OR6)
    - Haviv, Ron research, undated (Box OR7)
    - Haviv, Ron sales, 2000 (Box OR7)
    - Haviv, Ron, scripts 2000 (Box OR7)
    - History of Yugoslavia ethnic cleansing, etc. 1993 (Box OR7)
    - Human Rights Watch charges that U.S., NATO weapons play key role in Turkish abuses, 1995 21 Nov. (Box OR7)
    - Implementation of the Helsinki Accords Hearing before the Commission of Security and Cooperation in Europe, War Crimes and Humanitarian Crisis in the Former Yugoslavia, 1993 Jan. 25 (Box OR7)
    - International Criminal Tribunal of the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY), 1993-1997
      - Applications for leave to appeal and applications by the accused, 1996 Oct. (Box OR7)
      - Bulletin N.1, 1995 Dec. 15 (Box OR7)
      - Communications regarding indictments, 1995-1996 (Box OR7)
      - Court transcript, 1996 Jul. 24 (Box OR7)
      - "The Dayton Accord and the International Criminal Tribunal of the Former Yugoslavia," statement by Judge Antonio Cassese, 1996 June (Box OR7)
      - Decisions, 1995 Oct. 20 - 1996 Oct. 24, 1 of 2 (Box OR7)
      - Decisions, 1995 Oct. 20 - 1996 Oct. 24, 2 of 2 folders (Box OR7)
      - Directive on Assignment of Defence Counsel, 1996 June 25 (Box OR7)
      - Erdemovic, Drazen, miscellaneous court documents, 1996 (Box OR7)
      - General, 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box OR8)
      - Indictments 1-12, 1994-1995 (Box OR8)
      - Indictments, various, 1995 Feb.-1996 June (Box OR8)